
[
{
    "question": "An isolated electrochemical cell indefinitely generates an electrical current. How does this process violate the first law of thermodynamics, â€œthe conservation of energy?",
    "answer": "The first law of thermodynamics states that energy and matter cannot be created or destroyed, but only converted from one form to another. An electrochemical cell that generates electricity is an example in which energy is being created in a closed system without external energy input. Since energy is increasing without outside interference, the first law of thermodynamics is being violated.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/test-prep/mcat/chemical-processes/thermodynamics-mcat/e/thermodynamics-questions"
},
{
    "question": "What does Archimedes principle state and can this principle be applied to all fluids? What about objects of any shape or size?", 
    "answer": "Archimedes principle states that if a body is partially or wholly submerged, then it receives an upward thrust equivalent to the displaced fluid. All fluids, not just liquids and gases, can be covered by the Archimedes principle. However, as gases are less dense and have a weaker buoyancy factor, it is most often used in liquids. Also, objects of any shape or size shall be subject to this principle, as long as they are completely immersed in the liquid."
},
{
    "question": "What is the main function of a pressure regulator in a supersonic wind tunnel?",
    "answer": " In a wind tunnel, air flowing out of the tank results in a pressure drop. The pressure regulator ensures that the mass flow rate remains constant.",
    "explanation":"",
    "reference": "https://scholarworks.uark.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1020&context=meeguht"

},
{
  "question": "What are the distinct character differences between laminar and turbulent flow.",
  "answer": "Laminar flow is where the fluid flows in layers without heavy integration between the layers. Within each layer, the velocity, pressure, and other hydrodynamic properties remain unchanged. Contrarily, turbulent flow displays erratic movements that mix particles between the layers of fluids flowing.  ",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "How does the second law of thermodynamics describe why heat is transferred from a hot object to a cold object?",
  "answer": "The second law states that there exists a useful state variable called entropy. The change in entropy is equal to the heat transfer divided by the temperature. Thus, in a closed system, entropy tends to increase over time. When heat flows from a hot object to a cold object, it increases the overall entropy of the system, as the hot object loses heat and the cold object gains heat. This process tends to move the system towards a state of maximum entropy, which is the state of thermodynamic equilibrium.", 
  "explanation":"",
  "reference": "https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/second-law-entropy/"
},
{
  "question": "What is an example of a reversible process? What is an example of an irreversible process? ",
  "answer": "An example of a reversible process would be forcing a flow, with zero viscosity, through a constricted pipe. As the flow moves through the pipe, the pressure, temperature, and velocity would change, but these variables would return to their original values downstream. An example of an irreversible process is putting a hot object in contact with a cold object. Eventually, they both achieve the same equilibrium temperature. If we separate the objects they will not return to their original temperatures.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference": "https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/second-law-entropy/"
},
{
  "question": "Why does viscosity decrease with increasing temperature in a liquid?",
  "answer": "Viscosity, denoted by mu, varies strongly with temperature as it is closely linked to molecular motion. In a liquid molecules form bonds which enhances the transfer of momentum. As temperature rises, the kinetic energy of the molecules of the liquid increases. Thus, the particles move farther apart until bond forces no longer bind them together. Bond forces decrease and thus the transfer of momentum is reduced.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "What are the main assumptions associated with Fanno flow?",
  "answer": "Fanno flow is the adiabatic flow through a constant area duct where the effect of friction is considered. From this definition, we can identify that the main assumptions associated with Fanno flow are: the flow is steady, one-dimensional, and adiabatic through a constant-area duct, and the fluid is an ideal gas with constant specific heats.", 
  "explanation":"",
  "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanno_flow"
},
{
  "question": "Does the Mach number increase across an expansion fan? Why?",
  "answer": " Through an expansion fan, the Mach number increases, the static pressure decreases and the total pressure remains constant. This is because expansion fans are isentropic as a result of the area increase. Across an expansion fan, the velocity increases. Since Mach number can be determined by calculating velocity/area, this results in an increasing Mach number.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prandtl%E2%80%93Meyer_expansion_fan,https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/centered-expansion-fan/, https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/airplane/isentrop.html"
},  
{
    "question": "A pressure indicator column has a height of 2.25 meters and a density of 11300 kg/m^3. Determine the local atmospheric pressure. Assume acceleration due to gravity.",
    "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        rho = 11300\n        h = 2.25\n        g = 9.8\n        \n        # Apply the formula used to describe the pressure exerted by the weight of a gas or liquid in a column\n        atm_p = rho * h * g\n        print('The local atmospheric pressure is str(atm_p/101325)+' atm')\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure exerted by the weight of a gas or liquid in a column. Where h is the height above the observation point, rho is the density of the fluid, and g is the acceleration due to gravity on Earth.",
    "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/density-and-pressure/v/fluids-part-3"
},
{
    "question": "Consider water moving through a leveled pipe of varying diameter. Fluid enters the pipe with a velocity of 1.2m/s and exits the pipe with a velocity of 2m/s. The pressure into the pipe is 1650N/m^2. Assume laminar flow. Using Bernoulli's equation, calculate the pressure of water leaving the pipe.",
    "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        v1 = 1.2\n        v2 = 2\n        p1 = 1650\n        rho = 1000 # density of water\n        \n        # Recall Bernoullis Equation: \n        p1 + rho * h1 * g + 0.5 * rho * v1**2 = p2 + rho * h2 * g + 0.5 * rho * v2**2\n        \n        # Since the pipe is level, the height at either end of the pipe is the same, thus h1 = h2. Therefore, we can cancel out the terms involving h:\n        p1 + 0.5 * rho * v1**2 = p2 + 0.5 * rho * v2**2\n        \n        # Now substituting in our values we can solve for p2: \n        p2 = 0.5 * ((v1)**2 - (v2)**2) + p1\n        \n        print('The pressure of water that is exiting the system is str(p2)+' N/m^2')\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code uses Bernoulli's equation to determine the pressure leaving out of a pipe of varying diameter.",
    "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/fluid-dynamics/v/fluids-part-12"
},
{
    "question": "An oil of viscosity 0.97 poise and relative density 0.9 is flowing through a horizontal circular pipe of diameter 100 mm and of length 10 m. Calculate the difference of pressure at the two ends of the pipe, if 100 kg of the oil is collected in a tank in 30 seconds. Assume the flow is laminar.",
    "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        t= 30 # time\n        mu = 0.97/10 # Converting poise to N-s/m^2. 10 poise = 1 N-s/m^2\n        l = 10 # length \n        mdot = 100/t # mass flow rate\n        rho = 0.9 * 1000 # relative density is equal to 0.9(of 0:1)  \n        Q = mdot/rho # volume flow rate \n        d = 100/1000 # we must convert mm to m. 1mm is equal to 0.001m \n        r = d/2 # radius\n        A = (pi/4) * d**2 # area \n        v = Q/A # velocity\n        \n        # Since the flow is laminar we can apply the Hagen-Poiseuille equation to determine the pressure loss across a pipe:\n        Delta_p = (8 * mu * v * l)/(r**2)\n        \n        print('The loss in pressure is '+str(np.around(Delta_p,3))+'N/m^2')\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code determines the loss in pressure across a pipe such that t represents time, mu is viscosity, l is length, mdot is mass flow rate rho = is relative density, Q is volume flow rate, d is diameter, r is radius, A is area, and v is velocity.",
    "reference": "K., B. R., & Bansal, R. K. (2000). Textbook of fluid mechanics and hydraulic machines. Laxmi Pub."
},
{
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at a cruising speed of 300m/s at an altitude of 4500m where the atmospheric pressure is 60.25kPa and the ambient air temperature is 235.7K. The ambient air is first decelerated in a diffuser before it enters the compressor. Assuming both the diffuser and the compressor to be isentropic, what is the stagnation pressure at the compressor inlet? The constant-pressure specific heat cp is 1.005kJ/(kg*k) and the specific heat ratio, k, of air at room temperature is 1.4.",
    "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        v1 = 300 #velocity\n        p1 = 60.25\n        t1 = 235.7\n        cp = 1.005 * 1000 # conversion factor \n        k = 1.4\n        \n        # First we must determine the stagnation temperature, t0, at the compressor inlet:\n        t0 = t1 + ((v1 ** 2)/(2 * cp))\n        \n        # Then using the equation for stagnation pressure for ideal gases with constant specific heats:\n        p0 = p1 * ((t0/t1) ** (k/(k-1))\n        \n        print('The stagnation pressure at the compressor inlet is str(p2)+' kPa')\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation pressure at the compressor inlet such that v is the velocity, k is the specific heat ratio of air at room temperature, cp is the constant-pressure specific heat, t is the ambient air temperature, and p is the atmospheric pressure.",
    "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Ã‡engel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. page number 826. Chapter 17, example number 17-1"
},
{
  "question": "Air enters a diffuser with a velocity of 500m/s. Determine (a) the speed of sound and (b) the Mach number at the diffuser inlet when the air temperature is 30Â°C. Assume air at specified conditions behave as ideal gasses.",
    "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        R = 0.287 *1000 # gas constant of air converted from kJ/kg*K to m^2/s^2\n        k = 1.4 # specific heat ratio at 30 degrees Celsius\n        T = 30 + 273.15 # converting temperature in Celsius to temperature in kelvin\n        V = 500\n        \n        # (a) The speed of sound in the air can be expressed and determined using Hook's Law:\n        c = sqrt(k * R * T)\n        \n        # (b) The Mach Number is then easily determined using M = V/c\n        M = V/c\n        \n        print('The speed of sound is str(c)+' m/s')\n        print('The Mach number is str(M))\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code calculates the speed of sound in air such that R is the gas constant of air, k is the specific heat ratio at 30 degrees Celsius, T is the given temperature, and v is our given velocity.",
    "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Ã‡engel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. page number 829. Chapter 17, example number 17-2"
},
{
    "question": "A coffee thermos is initially closed and filled with 0.1m^3 of hot liquid at 366.15K and contains air at 0.2MPa. The thermos is then opened and left exposed to a space with a volume of  0.2m^3 at a temperature of 343.15K and 0.1MPa. Equilibrium is achieved adiabatically. What is the total mass of air? ",
    "answer": "\n        \n        import numpy as np\n        \n        p1 = 0.2 * 10**6 # converting MPa to Pa\n        v1 = 0.1\n        T1 = 366.15 \n        R = 287 \n        p2 = 0.1 * 10**6 # converting MPa to Pa\n        v2 = 0.2\n        T2 = 343.15\n        \n        # We can apply the Ideal Gas equation to find the mass inside the thermos and the mass of the room:\n        m1 =  (p1*v1)/(R * T1) \n        m2 =  (p2*v2)/(R * T2)\n        \n        # Then summing m1 and m2 to determine the total mass:\n        m_tot = m1 + m2\n        \n        print('The total mass of air is str(m_tot)+' kg')\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code solves for the total mass amongst two systems that have been interfaced and have reached equilibrium. Using the ideal gas equation such that P is the pressure, v is the volume, m is the mass, and T is the temperature. The total mass is determined by summing the individual masses of each system together.",
    "reference":"" 
},
{
  "question": "A heat engine receives heat from a source at 1200 K at a rate of 500 kJ/s and rejects the waste heat to a medium at 300 K. The power output of the heat engine is 180 kW. Determine the reversible power and the irreversibility rate for this process.",
    "answer": "\n        \n        import numpy as np\n        \n        waste = 300\n        source = 1200\n        q = 500 # volume flow rate\n        w_out = 180 # power output of heat engine\n        \n        # The reversible power for this process is the amount of power that a reversible heat engine would produce when operating between the same temperature limits, and is determined to be:\n        w_rev = (1- (waste /source)) * q \n        \n        # The irreversibility rate is the difference between the reversible power and the power output:\n        w_irrev = w_rev - w_out\n        \n        print('The reversible power for this process is str(w_rev)+' kW')\n        print('The irreversibility rate is str(w_irrev)+' kW')\n        ",
    "explanation": "This code solves for the reversible power and the irreversibility rate for work done on a heat engine. The waste is the heat rejected by the heat engine. The source is the heat received by the heat engine. The volume flow rate, q, is the rate in which the heat is received by the heat engine and the power output is the amount of work being output by the heat engine.",
    "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Ã‡engel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. page number 429. chapter 8, example number 8-3"
}
]